so today you're going to learn how you
can actually price arithmetic asian
options on electricity futures so we're
going to be using the australian
electricity market and not the traded
asx
average rate product but we're actually
going to be computing an
over-the-counter bespoke product which
is dependent on the average of the
closing price of the futures in the
contract period now we'll explain all
that shortly we're also going to be
looking at how you can use variance
reduction methods to get a more accurate
monte carlo options price without
increasing the complexity or the number
of simulations in your calculation we're
going to look at a control variant which
is going to be the analytical solution
for a geometric asian option so the
geometric asian option actually has a
closed form solution and we're going to
use that as a good static hedge for our
arithmetic option that we're trying to
price we're also going to look at what
happens when we have a combination of
antithetic and that control variant into
our simulation and what benefits we get
in terms of a reduction in the standard
error around our option price and the
computation time increase so without
further ado let's jump into it so again
we're using this risk neutral pricing
framework to be able to simulate risk
neutral asset parts in our monte carlo
simulation so that we can get a fair
price for our asian option so let's
import the dependencies here we've got
time numpy pandas scipy date time and
matplot lib now for a path dependent
options asians in this example we're
going to be pricing a european
arithmetic asian call option so here the
option pays the difference between the
arithmetic average of the price that
we're going to call 80 and the strike
price k and maturity t so the arithmetic
average is taken as the set of
observations of the asset price sti
which follows a gbm at dates t 1 3 to n
so here the asian average price option
has this arithmetic average of all the
observed prices at these observable
dates 1 through to n so that means that
here we have the payoff between our
times where we're going to be having
these average prices between t1 and t2
the payoff is going to be the max of
this arithmetic average minus k
so here's our asian call option sitting
here at time t we want to take the
average between time 1 and time 2
and we want to take the risk neutral
expectation
of this payoff discounted back to the
current time when we're paid so we're
paid at time two and we're currently
sitting here at time t so this payoff
here ct between t1 and t2 is dependent
on the forward prices that we're
observing our underlying between these
two times so here we're going to be
considering the australian electricity
market and we're going to be looking at
average rate options for q1 2023 now in
the national electricity market the nem
there are five separate markets for each
state and we're going to be valuing q1
2023 electricity asian options in the
new south wales market
so what we can see is that we've got the
futures contract price for q123 the last
settled price was
135.89 our current futures price for
q123 is the 135.89
now our time currently is the 22nd of
april 2020 and the actual period that
we're going to be taking the average
over is our q1 so that's a starting time
t1 of the 1st of january 2023 and then
an ending time a maturity date an expiry
date t2 which is the 31st of march 2023
now this is a 90-day contract period so
for the actual asx exchange product
which is the average rate option what
you're actually doing is you've got your
average rate option that's settled on
the end price of the futures contract
now the contract specification has an
average taken over all of the wholesale
prices so it takes the arithmetic
average of the wholesale prices and
that's how you settle against the
futures contract
so this is an average taken on 288
trading intervals for each day over that
contract period so that's 90 days over
288 trading intervals per day which
leads to an arithmetic average on your
wholesale price over 25
920 observations
so again we get our our current futures
contract price for the q123
which is settled at 135.89
now for the asian call price we're going
to be considering the strike that is
being traded here at 165 so we've got 50
50 megs here that have been traded and
the previous close was 18 dollars and
eight cents and that traded for an
implied volatility of
53.07
so that is the percentage volatility
that we're going to be using here in
this model so our initial parameters are
going to be the time which is today our
start time for the averaging which is
the start of the contract period and
then we've got the expiry that will stop
averaging over so that's our end date
our t2 then we've got the total amount
of days over this contract period 90. we
have to add one because when we take the
difference we lose one day
and then we're going to initialize the
parameters so we've got our initial
stock price or our futures price so
we've got
135.89 which is the current price we've
got our strike price which is 1.65 we've
got the time to maturity which is the
difference between today and then the
end average period t2 we've got the
annual risk free rate which we're
calling zero and we've got the
volatility which we've seen in the
market the implied volatility of that
traded product which is 53
the number of time steps here is the 90
days times 288 which is the 225
and 920 observations now we're going to
be simulating 1 000 prices now in
reality it's really important like i
said that this electricity average rate
options in australia and the new zealand
markets are actually settled against the
final futures prices so as futures are
settled against the arithmetic average
of the wholesale energy market price the
final futures prices as you get to the
end of the quarter actually converges on
the arithmetic average of the wholesale
energy price what does that mean well
that means that the reference price for
the asian style option exercise is
actually in accordance with this final
settlement price of the underlying
futures and it's determined on the third
business day after the final day of
trading so the method of option exercise
is that at this time if it's in the
money all all asian average rate options
are actually automatically exercised
into the underlying futures contracts
and cash settled now if they are not in
the money
and they're out of the money you're at
the money then this transfer is not uh
permitted so what does this mean well
this means that options can be priced
actually using the black shoals until
the end of the quarter and we'll
demonstrate that here so here's our
regular black shoals pricing formula
with our futures information and here
you can see that that was the traded
price with those parameters eighteen
dollars and eight cents
now to actually make this more
interesting and to actually demonstrate
the price even of an average rate option
because some futures are not pegged to
the arithmetic average like the
australian electricity market futures so
let's make this more interesting let's
say that we're going to trade
over-the-counter a bespoke average rate
option over this q 123 period with the
underlying as the same futures contract
now let's say that the average rate
option prices are actually determined by
the average of the daily futures across
the q 123 period so what do i mean i
mean that we have now this otc bespoke
product that we're going to trade over
the counter with someone else where
we've got our futures price today
and we're going to speculate what the
futures price is into the future so
we'll use our monte carlo simulation and
we're going to take the arithmetic
average across every day in the quarter
of that futures price and that's going
to be used to calculate our asian call
option so here's our slow step we're
actually going to step through things
day by day so now an n is not 25
920 here it's just discretized every day
so we've got 90 days
so here we've got the time from now till
time two is what we're going to call
time
t
to t2 and from time t to t 1 is the time
before we actually start averaging
so
the observed times is going to be
90 days between time 1 and time 2. so
these are called our observed starting
times we're actually going to append
zero to the start of this so that we can
get a difference array so we can
calculate the time between each one of
our observation times so here we're
going to have two empty numpy arrays
fulls of zeros where we've got our new
dt so our drift term and then our
volatility
squared with time so here we're going to
pre-compute the constants so over
this time period we're going to
calculate our respective constants and
the reason that they're not the same
every period is because we're jumping
from time 0 all the way to time 0.7
before actually taking the average so
hopefully that makes sense we've got
uneven time steps between our
observation we're going all the way from
time 0 to time 0.7
so we're computing all our respective
drift and then volatility terms between
these time periods our observations
which are then the same frequency every
day in that 90 day period in the quarter
we've then got our monte carlo
simulation where each
monte carlo simulation eye we're
initializing with our futures price
today and we've got our arithmetic sum
that's initialized at zero
then for all time periods we're just
going to simulate our epsilon so our
random normal our whiner process and
we're going to calculate our new futures
price at that time step
so we just take the respective drift and
then volatility term multiplied by our
whiner process we can then add this to
the arithmetic sum and we continue doing
this for the entire time of this
particular simulation
now at the end of time t2 so a 90-day
period we then take the arithmetic
average so we just divide that sum and
divide it by n so for the call price we
just take the max then of zero and the
difference between this arithmetic uh
average and k so here we're going to be
using this sum of ct so we can store our
the total sum of all the ct variables
and we'll use that to calculate the
expectation we've also get the sum of ct
squared so we can be able to calculate
the standard error so we're going to
compute the expectation which is we just
take over all of these monte carlo
simulations a thousand what is the
average discounted expectation uh price
of this arithmetic average rate option
and here we've got that it's
15.60 with a standard error of 0.1 1.3
with a computation time of 0.39
so now we're actually going to vectorize
this so we're going to use numpy arrays
to make it a little bit cleaner so
exactly the same initialization over
that 90-day period here we're actually
going to
have our numpy arrays um in actually
indexed in terms of n which is the time
steps and then m as well which is our
simulations so our drift and volatility
coefficients for each time period is
going to be the exact same for each
simulation
so that's why we're indexing by i for
the time but then keeping it the same
for the simulation then for the monte
carlo method we've got this random
normal of size
by the number of time steps by the
number of simulations so here we've got
an array of our deterministic plus our
diffusion multiplied by this whiner
process for each respective time period
at each simulation so this is our
changes in the stock price over time and
what we need to do is then we just need
to take the cumulative prod of all of
these exponential changes
across each path so we're taking the
cumulative prod of these
exponential
terms across each simulation path and
multiplying by s0 this means that when
we index by our final time point at each
of the simulations we get in the final
stock price outcome or futures price
outcome now to calculate the average
across all of the simulation paths we're
going to use not q prod vacuum sum so
now we're taking the cumulative sum
across all these price paths on axis
equals zero and then we're dividing by n
so that the final index point is the
arithmetic sum so now for all our
simulations we can use the numpy maximum
between 0 and then our final index time
arithmetic average minus k
we can then compute the discounted
expectation of this payoff and then the
standard error
so as you can see we've got 15.8 with a
standard error same as before it's just
been computed faster at point zero zero
eight so now we're going to be looking
at ways that we can actually complete
variance reduction techniques on this
monte carlo simulation so the first one
i'm going to look at is the antithetic
variance reduction technique so here
we've got our fast simulation but in our
monte carlo method here we're pricing
the complete version of a negatively
correlated variable so here you can see
that the diffusion component we have the
case where what happens if the future
price was completely simulated as the
negative correlation so we're decreasing
the complexity again and the computation
time because we've already simulated
the outcome of this whiner process but
we're using it again and imagining a
perfectly negatively correlated product
so we simulate these for every
simulation for every 1000 simulations
and remember it's kind of like two for
the price of one so what we're doing
here is we're reducing our variance by
only simulating the same number of
random variables
so then we compute the uh the prices
along all the paths so again we just
take the cumulative prod for these two
different cases and then we take the
arithmetic average for these two
different cases by using numpy sum
then we just take the average between
these two payoffs so just 0.5 times the
maximum of the first arithmetic average
minus this k and then the plus the
numpy maximum between 0 and then the
arithmetic average of the second case
minus k then we compute this enthalpic
discounted expectation of these prices
and then we get a call value which is
similar 15.909
but we get a reduction in our standard
error down from 1.3 to .86 so every time
we run this simulation
we're getting an improved accuracy
around our call value now one of the
best ways is to actually use a control
variant and one of the control variants
we can use is a geometric asian option
so obviously there's no analytical
solution for the arithmetic asian option
however there is for the geometric asian
option and this is because the geometric
asian
option is the average of a product of
normally distributed variables and
therefore itself is normally log
normally distributed
so for a geometric average price we've
got this gt which is the
product of all of these prices across
this time to the power of 1 over n so
this is the geometric average over this
series of prices
so the payoff at maturity is again going
to be priced the exact same way except
we're going to be substituting that
arithmetic average for the geometric
average
now this has a closed form solution
because essentially we can rearrange the
black shells formula to incorporate this
aspect that the geometric average is the
product of log normally distributed
prices which is log normally distributed
so we get this closed form solution of
this price here now
this is for the discrete monitoring case
where we're actually monitoring at
discrete times not continuously
monitoring and that's important because
the option that we're pricing has
discrete monitoring for the closing
price of the futures at every day in
that contract period
so here
for all of these variables n there's an
n number of observations to form the
average h is the observation frequency
and j is the number of observations that
are passed and in our case that's zero
so we can program that up and we can
call a function that's discrete
geometric asian where we're actually
passing all of our conditions for the n
h and j and then computing our geometric
discrete
asian option price and here you can see
that's about 15.95
for our case scenario here
so our tactic now for our control
variant is actually not going to be for
a delta control variant so
like we've done in the past we're
actually going to compute a portfolio
now the portfolio is going to be the
difference between the arithmetic and
the geometric asian option
so this is a very good static hedge for
the arithmetic option and instead of
actually computing the delta at each
time period which would be increased
computation we're going to simulate this
portfolio that's long the arithmetic
option and short the geometric asian
option then at the end when we've
computed the
discounted expectation of the price all
we need to do is add back on the
analytical solution of the geometric
asian option price to our monte carlo
portfolio simulation so let's get into
it we price exactly the same way so now
we're calculating gt which is just the
geometric average so we're taking the
cumulative product of all these stock
prices along each path
to the power of one over n and again
we're going to index by the final time
period
so here is our portfolio we've got our
arithmetic option minus our geometric
option payoff and we're doing that for 1
monte carlo simulations here we take the
discounted expectation of this portfolio
payoff and then we add back on the
discrete geometric asian price so now
what you'll see is that our call value
has is around the same now as 16.25 but
our standard error has been in
incredibly reduced from 0.8 all the way
down to 0.02
so an incredible reduction in the
standard error so now we're going to
look at the antithetic and the control
variant of the geometric average option
and see how that helps in terms of
variance reduction for our monte carlo
technique so now we're simulating we're
pre-computing the constants just as we
have done before
for our monte carlo simulation we have
two price paths which are negatively
correlated with each other so that's the
antithetic component here so we've got
two price paths one and two and we're
computing the arithmetic average for
each of those prices and we're computing
the geometric average for both of those
price paths for each of the 1000
simulations so then we're going to
calculate our portfolio payoff so we're
going to take the average between the
two portfolios remember each portfolio
holds a it's long an arithmetic option
and short the geometric option and then
it's got two price paths one and two so
we're just taking the average between
those two portfolios now we're going to
calculate the discounted expectation of
this portfolio payoff over all these
1000 simulations and then we can compute
our standard error and then we add back
our discrete geometric asian price to
this portfolio and now we've got a very
accurate price of
16.27 with a standard error of
0.02 now the computation time has gone
up so let's compare these variants
reduction methods and the computation
time that it's taken because again you
know we've decreased the standard error
but we've increased the relative
computation time
so just for a um an idea of what the
slow estimate took so here are all our
asian call option value prices on the
left hand side here we've got the
standard errors that have been reduced
as we've introduced these measures so
we've used the fast estimate so our
vectorized array to benchmark our
variance reaction methods and we did
this because this is a fairer comparison
as these have been vectorized so just so
you know that if you do not vectorize it
it's about 50 times slower to run
our for loops for all the time periods
and for all those simulations so much
better to use
numpy arrays for this as we move to the
antithetic variant what you get is a
reduction in your standard error by
about 1.5 for a relative computation
time of 1.25 multiple so the geometric
control variant is where you see very
significant gains
for a time relative time
computation of only 1.4
so just a little bit more than doing the
antithetic variate you can actually get
a 55 56 magnitude decrease in your
standard error and that's because the
geometric
average option is such a good
price indication of your arithmetic
average option
so it's a very very good static hedge
therefore we get very significant gains
in terms of this reduction in the
standard error now obviously you can see
the benefit when then you add the
antithetic variate with the geometric
control variant you get this further
increased reduction
of a multiple of 66
but that does take an increased
computation time of two times uh just
what our normal vectorized estimation
was so again just to summarize we took
our own interpretation of an over the
counter bespoke energy traded product
which was the average of the futures
contract between over the time period of
that quarter and we took the average of
the closing price of the futures each
day so we used monte carlo simulation to
be able to get the ford prices our
futures prices between those periods and
take the average over those price parts
and compute the asian call payoffs and
then we actually used a variety of
variance reduction techniques to be able
to get a more accurate price over this
asian option
so hopefully you learnt a lot and i look
forward to seeing you in the next
episode